[Music]
hello and welcome to the junkyard
knowledge is power
[Music]
ahoy that is the new intro if you
haven't heard it yet I'm gonna leave it
a minute long for the next few episodes
so I get to enjoy it and then I'll
shorten it and make it like 30 seconds
or 20 seconds whatever and then also
what I'm gonna start doing is mentioning
some recommendations in the form of like
TED Talks books articles blogs
meditations things that I'm always into
things that I'm always learning that I
can quickly drop in at the beginning of
each episode just something for you to
look into and maybe make you life a
little bit better so this TED talk today
I'm gonna recommend is breathe to heal
by Max Strom it's 18 minutes and 33
seconds it's on YouTube and it's
fantastic enjoy the episode wieners does
this sound better than what where's the
echo 8 yeah dude audio and onazi I
should stop obsessing over sounds fine
this is what it was before
yeah this one hey this sounds good I had
to dive deep and make sure that all the
other things weren't tried first so I
just learned on the internet that
there's three kinds of empathy cognitive
emotional and compassionate empathy and
cognitive empathy is how I feel is when
you view you can feel other people and
see their perspective but you don't
actually feel anything at all emotional
is when you see their perspective and
you feel all of their emotions and then
compassionate empathy is kind of a
mixture of both it's when you usually
understand by empathy feeling someone's
pain and taking action to help ya so you
feel it notice it and then you step in
to somehow mitigate or solve the problem
that is causing this and apparently that
you need to find a balance between these
things finding the balance cognitive
empathy can often be considered under
emotional emotional empathy by contrast
is over emotional in exercising
compassionate empathy we can find the
right balance between logic and emotion
okay why don't you give your what would
you define empathy as
do you turn that off so it's not
distracting yes nice
what would I define up for use uh well
it is just feeling the emotions of
others or their current state of being
like and uh have you always be in this
state well I think that sometimes is
detrimental if you are over feeling like
if you see somebody in pain and you just
take all of that for yourself you can
now be overloaded by an emotion that is
not necessarily yours right holding the
burdens of others hmm that's interesting
yeah it's like you can't hold your stuff
and everybody else's stuff I think that
like mothers tend to do this just
because of who they are obviously they
want to like hold the weight of
everything they can like for their kids
and for other people on them like that
I'm just John refining motherly and that
motherly trait they want to like try to
hold everybody else's pain a lot of
times they can handle a lot more it
seems like but it's not this is not
super good I feel like we I was telling
you before this that we I think we kind
of understand words like or
misunderstand words like empathy and
being empathetic and getting them
confused with sympathy and things like
that I think that emotional empathy or
this feeling empathy it probably has a
good side to it but if you let it
overwhelm you or take in too much of
other people's emotions you're just
going to just going to be detrimental
for you I personally have the other
problem like I will have a lot of
empathy but I actually won't feel any
emotion which is just be a stoic weirdo
yeah which I feel like it's more of a
dude thing this is very over
generalization but let's say masculine
energy masculine it's more of a
masculine thing to do is to if you're
going to be empathetic you understand
the situation see it grapple with it but
don't actually internalize any of it
which leads to more calloused responses
but on the other end if you're going to
over feel it as equally as bad for a
different reason I'm sorry to be
touching this can you elaborate more on
that
well I could give me an example which
one of someone doing exactly what you
were just saying okay let's say one of
my friends they I guess they just lost a
loved one and you understand that this
is this is sad but you have a very hard
time emotionally comforting them because
you just don't feel what they're feeling
you haven't allowed yourself to which
this happens to me a lot that was a very
extreme example and death is of course
but that no that's a good bike you know
yes simplest large magnitude of events
but I run into this a lot like very
highly empathetic but I am very
extremely bad at comforting people
because I just don't have I don't share
those feelings do you think it comes
across as like you not being sensitive
or you not sometimes when people aren't
sharing exactly what we're feeling they
see it as like are you heartless like
how are you not feeling exactly what I'm
feeling how is this not terrible yes I
mean I've been characterized as not
being sensitive even by myself so I feel
like there's a balance between these two
things like in order to be a more
effective person and interpersonal
relationships you definitely need to
feel someone's emotion but you can't let
it overwhelm you because it's I mean it
really isn't your it's not your emotion
to be feeling in the first place right
yeah we can just walk around just taking
other people's emotions but what are
your experiences with this I don't know
I think that I I feel like oh this chair
again man this chair I feel like that I
that I used to have trouble absorbing
things it would overwhelm me like one
other someone else was going through
something I would feel what I would call
like oh so much humanity for them so
much sympathy so much empathy whatever
it wasn't my brain like I would almost
feel - like they're crying like I want
to cry - like oh my gosh you must hurt
what you're going through I
I want you almost want to like force
your emotions - under
stand and work out what they're feeling
just so you can like really sympathize
with them and but sometimes it's it's
bad you know if you if you can't really
learn how to sharpen that tool and you
know sometimes you get overwhelmed with
with other people's emotions and it
mixes in with yours and you're kind of
like unsure of what you're even upset
about you just feel out of control in a
sense do you think that's led you to be
a more emotional person mmm I think I'm
inherently more emotional emotional I
think that if we're talking
masculine-feminine I think I'm probably
more feminine I think that just like the
nature of my upbringing right you know
and I have three older sisters I've
lived in a house with I think seven to
nine women for a couple years at a
younger age I think I'm just more more
you know in touch with my emotions seems
like the worst sentence to say and in
the thing here but I don't know
well let's start with that let's start
with that subject there Spencer
welcome to the junkyard love podcast
that's the cool thing when I lose a
train of thought when is your podcast
you can make well when you're up with
the intro I'm gonna keep that beginning
- good morning I am I'm glad you came
over today I have been a little under
the weather with the wetter I've been
under the wetter and I I think it was
what we decided was gastric gastrin itis
gas turd we just sick you just
essentially I've just not been feeling
super great and it's not good so
obviously it's it's cool to notice not
cool but it's interesting to notice when
you're sick your body sick you know your
brain immediately sucks dude like you
can't just like read your favorite book
you just want to watch super mindless
stuff and not even lift your head and
that just tells you it's just a reminder
of like man your body is so connected to
your brain your thoughts like the the
fog that I've had the last couple days
like I just I'm like man and I have like
six podcast episodes to edit and I'm
gonna do this I'm gonna do that and I
just like pretty much just smelled my
own farts and up like uploaded one
episode that's about it the last four
days three days so anyway I'm feeling
better now I'm not just crying in my own
tears of self complaint which is what I
tend to do when I'm sick in that's awful
so if when you're sick listener if you
just complain a lot just notice that
you're doing that and don't do that
that's a note to myself couple days ago
Spencer we had a couple things we wrote
down would you like to jump right into
this well empathy was one of them if you
want to elaborate on that or if we
covered that I think we covered that
okay I think it is important for people
to know epithets just end with that why
is it important for people to know
empathy in this world like in this and
weird navigating society well yeah well
you need to be able to relate to people
and where they're coming from in general
to actually develop interpersonal
connections and have quality not
one-sided conversations and do you feel
when we misunderstand our empathetic
mind and body we
we instead actually just share their
feelings like we're comforting them by
like okay you're sad I'm gonna feel sad
too like you're gonna jump off the
bridge I'm gonna jump off the bridge
with you are we are we just joining them
and they're feeling sometimes instead of
like understanding them and really
helping like what does this person need
they need comfort of course but
sometimes I think we just immediately
matched their feelings and sink right
into that call that sympathy and I think
that's not super good yeah I think that
you should feel it but then take actions
to try to mitigate it like if you can
help them do it but I mean you can't
necessarily relieve the burden of
someone's emotions by feeling them as
well it might make it worse that works
all wallowing yeah so I agree I mean if
on an ethical level if your goal is to
reduce the amount of suffering total
which I've deduced that that's what I
think everyone's life decisions should
be or at least mine you in turn
suffering because someone else is is not
reducing that even if it does sound
selfish you are increasing the suffering
so if you could find a way to reduce
everyone's suffering it's gonna be the
most ethical and helpful right yeah if
you just look at like if there's a
certain level of of suffering total in
the room like don't even think about you
or the other person in the room just
think about the room itself the
suffering in general in there are you
gonna go add to it
or are you gonna go take away from it
how about that less would be good else
would be gonna take less let's do this I
want to talk about projection
projections no I like projectors and I
got one time for Christmas the very
bright mm-hmm what I noticed I was at a
concert last weekend was it Led Zeppelin
Nickelback yes both actually
back-to-back was great but so it was an
electronic concert and people are pretty
boisterous there and they make some pre
bold fashion choices and so I made a
thong I was just like super cool with it
I'm super cooled nudity I think that
everyone to be more cool with it but I
was thinking about how people would
perceive that in accordance now if they
would do that or not
so if you're a person that you would do
that to get attention you would assume
that they're doing that to get attention
because you're just projecting your [__]
onto them but what if they're not like
this is not a it's not a truth in the
world necessarily like we don't as
humans you only navigate you so you
don't have true empathy so you can't
100% live in someone shoes and
understand all the way why they do
things especially not off just seeing
them so we kind of as humans if we're
not careful just wander through the
world and project all our dumb bad [__]
onto other people do you I think that a
lot of people don't realize that they're
doing it like like when we're when you
so you said you're like I noticed that I
was like I noticed that I saw this man
right and then so did you immediately
judge him in a negative way or not you
didn't see I don't care about it
like I've done a lot of these things I'm
very like a fluid and open so it didn't
bite me but I did think about I don't
know it just sparked the thought like
this is a very flamboyant way to dress
and I would assume the reaction from
some people would be like he's doing
this for attention but you can't surmise
that and olders and you jump to that
conclusion I mean of course you take
like real-world data and you know some
people do that but you also are
projecting yourself onto that right and
in arguments that happens like if some
pino someone peak like angry people
people that have a temper they will
project a lot of their anger on other
people as well like they assume that or
people that are spiteful they assume
Pete other people are doing things to
them in a spiteful fashion because they
might be they might do that as well and
you kind of just get in this you assume
because all you have is you to judge or
you to go off of that other people are
acting in ways because that's the way
that you would but that's not
necessarily true and I don't know I
didn't come to a conclusion on how to
deal with this I just had a large
epiphany about it mm-hmm because we
can't actually have to remedy like you
can't live in someone else's skin so how
do you how do you mitigate this and I
guess judge less would be the conclusion
I think I think that the big thing there
is like just the fact that you noticed
it and then
continue to no notice it so if it's
noticing that you're judging someone and
then asking yourself like you know what
what you did like you you happen to
notice oh this is where other people
would obviously judge and you wondered
why to yourself I think that when you
see anything that anybody else is doing
in you
there's a different state of being than
walking around doing what you're doing
enjoying your life smelling your own air
like these seeing the things that you
want to see with your eyes and walking
around having judgments about people
whether they're good or bad they're
there's a way of going about your life
where people are just walking past you
you're not noticing I mean in a thong
you think that's just the duties doing
something other than what I'm doing and
you just he keeps going he doesn't even
interrupt your thoughts so judgment
almost interrupts your thoughts like it
takes you out of what you're trying to
do if you're just trying to walk to the
bathroom what you're trying to do is
walk to the bathroom not have six
different judgments about six different
people who are wearing six different
colored thongs these are things that of
course you have a look around you could
enjoy your life because if you're in the
right perspective as you're walking
through you can say like that's
wonderful that guy's doing that that's
cool that girl's doing that whatever you
could even talk to them interact with
them but I think that some of us are in
a weird
maybe flipping the words parasympathetic
state but when a weight's person thetic
fight-or-flight person that ik is eating
sleeping meditating okay deep breath
sympathetic is a fight-or-flight nerves
so if we're in a sympathetic state let's
say your object up yours you're walking
around kind of you're judging people
because it's do you think it's maybe
like a defense tactic like I think that
there is a internal want to be normal
and then shun other things that aren't
normal so if you see something that
somebody's doing that you don't deem as
normal needs it's comforting for you to
go to the guy beside you inhale you like
look at this dude like this guy's
ridiculous because now you're staying in
this tribe you're staying with the
humans you know I think these people are
accepting you you guys are bonding
together on a ridicule or a hatred of
this person because of this one thing
that you don't even know the actual
origin of because I mean they always say
the hates more rallying than love and I
think it is easier it is it's we think
that we need to yeah its imagine being
in a like this is your group you have a
hundred and fifty people 150
and you lean over to number 32 because
you see number 58 he's wearing the gold
thong and you're like hey it fits you
too
look at this can I wear hey we're still
gonna do the shirt entire thing right
right and he's like yeah like as an
idiot anyway go gay ever still doing a
shirt and tie thing right like you're
just making sure essentially like if you
break this down to super primitive
[__] seems like you're just making
sure like can't we're not all gonna do
that because that if I was doing that
that would mean this that's what our
brain is actually thinking but we bring
it back into this confused terminology
of I think this thing about this person
because this you're just affirming
yourself to yeah in a not so healthy way
I mean I got together as a bunch of my
friends that I've known for real a long
time and it's very easy to just like
slip back into being a [__] you know
he's got people watching you something
haha
and I noticed it and it was even after
that it was just I kept doing it like
you just go on people watch I find
myself people watching a lot of concerts
about depending on who I'm with and I
notice that when I go off alone I have
much more I don't know just a much more
like peaceful like relaxing more in
taking ice I'm just more aware but not
as judgy I'm not around all these people
that I'm close with and I think that
might be some to it I don't really want
to conclude that but yeah I mean I
definitely feel more judgy when I'm with
other people than I am when I'm alone
like especially it like a DDM concert
cuz it's just [__] ridiculous like
it's just a spectacle of people and
personalities and there's so much to
look at and it's so easy when you're
just like with your friends like hey
look at that guy moving like that but
it's actually none of your business you
know like it's actually not what you
came here you came here to like listen
to music and I think that it pulls palsy
out of it I agree I think a camaraderie
is super important but I'm we do got to
watch ourselves though like what am I
getting pulled into like let's not let's
not go five days into being this just
like crazy gorilla dude if I don't
really want to do to be that person
overall I mean there's certain places
where you just kind of like let go and
just be a dummy sometimes I think but be
respectful about it and
and be in your own world I think it was
great though I had a good time yeah it
was fun yeah I really enjoyed just like
being a little [__] for a while
hanging out with my friends yeah you
talked about how because you you do like
your alone time but you say you're an
extroverted person you are an extrovert
yeah I'm extremely recharged by people
yeah in general but I also am recharged
by being alone like I need a 70/30
balance of this like 70% of time I rely
people around people I really like when
I speak out loud like the exertion of it
I really enjoy the feeling it makes me
feel very good and I like to help people
as well and just like talk about stuff
and convey ideas so interactions like
that I really enjoy but very like common
interactions you have with people you
don't know I really don't enjoy it all
that it's just like a nagging harassment
on being alive or it's just not it's
just not helpful at all it's it's just
doesn't get anywhere and everyone knows
the dance like hey how you doing today
mm-hmm nice and then you don't actually
have anything that you know about that
you have in common yet and it's just or
it's somebody that you're fully aware
that you're not gonna get necessarily
along with all the way you're down on
the same wavelength I mean that's okay
mm-hmm those just suck the life out of
me do you think like when the other
person is not like aware of the non-dual
ness in the in the conversation or the
the dual illness in the conversation
like they're not aware that they're not
your best friend or something
seeing those situations huh I don't know
it's more just like if you've got okay
let's say you work somewhere and there's
just like a customer that comes in
sometimes and you like kind of know them
and they just everyone's been held
hostage by like a heist someone they
knew from high school that they knew
kinda you run over to the grocery store
and you guys both because of social
norms and being polite just get locked
into speaking together mm-hmm
and both of you know it's like we want
to go it was rough I mean I really do I
really wish you well but this is
draining of my time and energy mm-hmm
and I know it sounds super rude but I
feel like this is a really
shared experience no it is I don't think
it's rude I think if it was one-sided
but I think a lot of this is two-sided
and the two-sided is not like dude I
don't want to talk to you it's just like
let's just break down this barrier of
like we need to act like we've been
long-lost best friends and all these
things like we could you know I am
always like very happy to see people
that I haven't seen in a long time but
there's a lot of like you know what this
is and I know what this is like I
haven't seen you in forever I do know
you exist I know your name that's okay
we used to hang out we maybe have a
number on out I think just like taking
things for what they are instead of
treating every single relationship
exactly as this one baseline you know I
would be super stoked to see people if
that was just the norm but people that I
only count know like a ban like how your
kids yeah how's your life going like
awesome and I hope you have a good day
it was really good to see you alright
gone like if you gave me a button and
you a button and we were just like kind
of friends at one point of time like
seven years ago and that button would
allow us to abort the conversation
without anyone knowing you press the
[__] out of it yeah I'm like it right
like way way before the 30 minutes of
hanging out and Safeway I think that I
think that a lot of times our
conversations get a little weird because
of social media yeah I'm gonna go ahead
and blame social media for something
else right now
so being off social media I wasn't
caught up on people so I don't know
who's pregnant I don't know who isn't
pregnant I don't know who just got
married
I don't know who dyed their hair purple
and I don't know her like it's so these
things in the they seem like things you
don't really lock in like as you're
scrolling they're kind of just like
quick like ran out okay that person that
person and it's not that you don't care
about these people like these are your
distant friends you're like cool it's
it's nice to know this information about
these people but then when you see them
you're almost left with nothing to talk
about because it's not surprised so like
when I was off social media like if I
saw so me in the grocery store I haven't
seen their face I haven't heard of them
like I've been so into just my own world
like you forget this person exists
completely like I'm not kidding you you
think it's a different I've been so
connected to social media for so long
it's it's like a different thing when
you completely forget that these people
even exist you see them and like oh dude
what
man like how are you you get it quick
you know you get five minutes they tell
them that you hear about their kids
you get reminded of their kids names
there's all these things and you walk
away I just happy as a client and say in
a grocery store I think that social
media and feeling the need to stay so
connected at all times because this is
something we all got so connected but we
didn't I can't make should we always
weaken is that super good and I think
that it makes these little conversations
more weird we're like do I address that
I know you do I say that I have you on
Facebook do I just bring up what you
most recently posted and I talk about
that do I apologize for not liking your
post because that means something it's a
weird thing I am I know anyway what I'm
rounding about is I think that not
having social media makes it toward
these conversations where you do bump
into each other it's never the [__]
it's like you know I don't have to you
know sometimes I'm not my 100 like
sometimes I'm really just not in the
best conversation mode but it doesn't
mean anything inherently and if I do run
into you I think just letting that
genuine wonder and genuine thing pop up
of like I'm not trying to not go see
with someone at the store I'm not trying
to see someone at the store I'm not even
thinking that this person exists these
people exist I'm living my life and then
if I do bump into this person what a
joyous occasion that I can I can I can
represent and deal with when it comes
along and I'll tell you that at most the
time it's been great it's been genuine
it's honestly like I'm like dude great
to see you
it's a hug it's a like I don't know
everything about this person as I just
walked away they didn't have to give me
all of their Facebook updates for the
last year and in a printout and I had to
read it while they just stood there in
front of me I just had a conversation
with them and that's all that it was I
think on the flip side of that too
though I would say it's kind of contrary
what it just said but 50% of the
conversation end up having I really do
enjoy when I run into people and I end
up this is kind of why I despise it too
because I will actually just I value
just personal interaction a lot so I
will spend Wayne
more time than I have speaking of this
person so now it's all it's it's never
that helpful for me because if I want to
talk to my mind up talking too long I
don't have the time to but then also
with social media your second hand
connected to a bunch of people you
wouldn't normally know so in your like
weird Twitter friends with them you know
like you like like their post and you
reply to each other sometimes we never
meet them but then if you run into them
you feel this weird pressure you're like
I know this person
kind of it's like I don't at all though
but we're about to talk for awhile and
it's not gonna be super comfy yeah I
think treating that as honestly I think
as simple as like this conversation here
Spencer like just noting it like hey
guys this exists it's okay we can like
it's not the end of the world to be kind
of awkward for a second and then just
like maybe you're gonna stumble over
like hey Cynthia that's your name right
like what and then you could just be
like oh yeah okay I don't know you
totally and then you just go on to
whatever conversation happen it's like
don't let that awkwardness represent who
you are like don't be nervous because
because I find myself you know social
anxiety really kicks in for me a lot of
times I get very nervous the question
you don't remember my name do you
like like someone saying that to me is
is it it breaks my heart because I'm
like please it will not not as much more
but it used to because I'm like dude
like that's not who I am like I I don't
I don't mean it like that I just have a
lot of other things that I'm thinking
about I didn't fully remember your name
like there's so many different reasons
it doesn't mean that I dislike you or my
interactions with you or not genuine
like I tried to be present and mean what
I say when I'm looking at people and
interacting with them it's not [__]
but that doesn't mean that I can
remember everybody's name those sort of
things so I think this we address it
like letting those things be in the air
like for our age people and just like
dude it's [__] okay that we have
weird relationships with people because
of the internet now that are extended
for maybe longer than they would have
been before and we keep them as that
like we can we can deal with them as
they come up
and normally weird
we live in a very odd time for
communication yes I really think that
it's just we communicates so different
than any other
generation before us and it leads to a
lot of I mean cuz there's no rules in
any of this you know communication was
pretty dialed in for the internet like
everybody there's a system everyone kind
of knew how to navigate it it's been
going on for thousands of years then all
of a sudden we're just all all this hive
mind together doing this big group thing
but we don't actually know how to speak
to each other at all groupthink hive
mind what do you mean by words like that
so hive mind is like a big collective
brain of thoughts and it's kind of what
the internet is it's just like this
collective consciousness of bound
together brains creating one singular
one singular brain like a hive of brains
so like a hive mind if you compare it to
be ether obviously a hive situation yeah
I mean they essentially all they use
like pheromones and sense to all
communicate together but they work in
unison essentially mm-hmm towards the
one vehicle to bring to to to pollinate
the yeah to survive and whatnot right so
we're hive mind we can have hide by now
especially because we're all connected
to the phone phone is touching our body
at most times of the day it's really
just an extension of you at this point
like your social media is low-key an
extension of you whether you like it or
not I mean that is mean it portrays you
and I actually grapple with this a lot
like what is even the utility of of this
this thing well I I think even farther
than that is do even I'll have to have
social media like why do you have social
media so super good question to ask
yourself I think about this all the time
I remember I look at it like is this
like what is what's the goal like I talk
to everyone that I like to talk to
already like why do I need this
they like all my friends see all my
photos because they were there most the
time and the thing that I put up here
and the image that I create on
especially Instagram is the worst it's
the most curated vapid face value
nonsense out all of them because at
least with my favorite
it's also my favorite because it's
pretty and it's got pictures and it's
like hey look at me but like this
doesn't actually portray who I am or any
nuance of my being so it's it's like a
shitty advertisement for you you know
this is not it's just not you really it
can be even especially if you keep
pictures for a long time like the
pictures you posted two years ago
you're probably cringe at really hard
and I do when I look at my social medium
like this is not who I am at all like
I'm really at like the caption that I
put here I don't like I don't like this
photo like I don't like how this is
portraying me like this whole thing is
like this though and I feel like a lot
of people also feel the same I would
assume like this is just not does not me
why do I have this what's the utility of
this I mean it kind of blatantly shows
what what we're doing here anyway that
if you think about it like what what is
any of this you yeah this I guess it's
the same about rejecting yourself though
I mean it's just like an ultra
projection of you that's way more
concrete than you actually projecting
yourself to the world that more people
can see I mean it's just an extension of
the absurdity of being alive you think
that we're we're obsessed with wanting
to preserve these things we're we're
obsessed with saying like no no this is
me
it's our ego mine's like on the internet
say saying this is as much me if I make
this person this person that's who if I
make this person on social media amazing
then that will be me that's me
absolutely okay when I was a middle
school as a small kid I was like I was
popular how long's everyone bow into a
small school I knew everybody and I
wasn't like that guy it was always just
I never felt that I got a lot of social
attention even though I probably did I
got way more than a lot of people but I
was never like I want to be that guy so
I'm you get social media you only post
the pictures of you have music festivals
pictures of your car because you lift
some weights and just like all the stuff
it's like yeah look at me it's never any
of the vulnerable moments never you
being sad at 4:00 a.m. it's just the
perfect projection of your highlight
reel so people say that you're awesome
that's what it was for me I just want
you to look at me right that's I mean
that's what Instagram is look at look at
what this dude it is remember in
Highschool you ever have like those end
of your slideshows you know like someone
just make some like it's probably like
good riddance bye-bye Green Day and or
sixpence kiss me even in some cases and
it's just like what we're trying to do
with social media is we're just trying
to have like a slideshow that's going
all the time and we're trying to make
that represent who we are and it's like
do you need a slideshow why do you even
have a slideshow is this well you're
getting validation people you don't care
about but but how do we realize that
that's that's what it is you know that
like these are what we're being fed our
own insecurities in a way sometimes it
just feels good it's comfortable to just
put all your stuff on the internet and
be this person and flex super-hard
mm-hmm because it just doesn't show the
vulnerability of being alive and we kind
of I mean you see it in a rap culture
you just champion being like bawling out
like being that guy like it's a very
boisterous and in-your-face and I feel
like our generation was really like
growing up on that as well so even
before social media like the urge to be
looked at was present in pop culture and
then this comes along and just time to
follow what we know like all these cool
people that we idolize is what they do
they just flex as hard as they can right
well I mean you notice a lot of them now
though I mean within the last probably
two years
I mean you've probably seen it in
different ways to even just following
like even the the EDM guys I get a lot
of people are unwinding a bit more and
kind of realizing a lot of the same
things like wait what is this like even
famous people are like this sucks
I got like you know logic toxic
extensively in some of the h3 interviews
about like social media mike-mike stud
has a podcast now and that him and his
boys mentioned that towards beginning
Chris drama Pat who Rob Dyrdek's cousin
like he's got like spiritual [__] and
they talked about like social media now
and I'm like in how they wanted to post
all their cars money clothes and hoes
dan Bilzerian even within the last year
has talked about like dude if I'm on
social media in in two years kill me or
something which is an aggressive Tamra's
area
let's say anything to say but he can do
whatever he wants it's interesting I
think that the truth of the matter is of
what I what I'm always trying to boil
down with the social media thing because
it's kind of like just why do you have
it you don't need it and it's it's not
incredibly beneficial it is a it is it's
a hobby
it's a it's something you do you know
like some people on their free time when
they're on the couch they look up the
latest golf balls that came out because
they're a golfer and they study
extensively about that or they have they
follow a subreddit about golfing they
find some app about golfing because
that's their passion but what a lot of
us do now our hobby is following social
media our hobby is now social media our
hobby is making sure our slideshow is
pristine and mean at all times and we
build our life around it I just it's
cool and it is a cool thing that we can
do and there's like when it comes to the
business side the monetary side of all
these things it's so sick but I think
that it's capturing us in ways that we
didn't realize again what you're just
saying like the I guess just realizing
why we have it like like we've always
had it and like of course I want social
media it's cool then a couple years
later you're like wait well how do you
like why am i why is this what is this
why are we doing this what's the what
why is this worth all of this time
besides these this little little doses
of happiness here and there how is this
good for my overall life is this
something that I want to choose to use
we even take a step back from that and
that's why do you do anything I just
start analyzing your life why do you do
stuff yeah just all the little habits
you have all the little things that you
decide to put time and effort into like
why do you do them mm-hmm yeah what are
they leading up to yeah and if you if
it's just goes yeah I like it and it's a
healthy thing for you yeah keep doing it
I don't think social mean is all bad I
think there's a healthy way to use do
almost anything to be honest and if it
doesn't detract from your life you
manage it well and you really just use
it to communicate excellent tool but I
the way it's literally designed to not
be used like that it's just hyper
addictive it's trying to sell you stuff
it's really colorful
and it just kind of keeps you in this
like he said she said gossip being kind
of mindset because you just are looking
at others and you're either talking [__]
or feeling bad that they're doing better
than you know and I feel like that's how
most people are social media is never
actually emotionally detracted for me
it's it's actually it makes me feel good
that's I'm on that side like social
media reaffirms this [__] out of who I
am but a lot of people I know I really
detract from their life because they
just feel bad about the current
situation and I don't think that's good
do you think do you think that being on
Facebook when you wake up in the morning
and you check facebook can you see
something that you really don't agree
with is that enough to activate here
your fight-or-flight now but I do think
it really impacts your day because when
you wake up you're in such a sensitive
state to information and just your
brainwave state is just really receptive
and you're just a really sensitive being
for a while so people are often really
grumpy in the morning and really like
emotionally fragile and and just I guess
just soft but if you wake up and you
just get blasted with whatever there's
some someone's trying to tell you it's
mostly negative because that's what gets
clicks and sells stuff I don't think
it's helpful I stopped looking at my
phone in the morning and it's made my
life a lot better like a lot of people
will just sit and scroll for 40 minutes
okay here's here's what I mean
I mean I'm gonna expand on that that
question that I asked you with an
analogy of course okay so you're in your
backyard it doesn't matter if you just
woke up or whatever you have your phone
in your hand and your heart rate is slow
and your which would be and what what
rate would you be in if your heart rate
slowed and you're calm you're thinking
clearly probably parasympathetic what
kind of estate okay and then you're
chilling and you're fine you're not
really thinking about much and then
corner of your eye a wolf approaches you
in your backyard and it's it's far away
what happens then you're in this calm
state and your heart rates gonna go up
right your heart rate picks up your
breath rate picks up you become more
acute you feel your adrenals dump so you
become tense
okay lockup and you're thinking what am
I gonna like I gotta figure out what to
do next have to run from this wolf I
have to fight him I have to lay on the
ground and put my head tucked in I don't
know what to do with Wolf's I haven't
read about Wolf's whatever and in the
same sense while these things are going
on you're in this your hearts elevated
you're just thinking of how do I survive
this situation well during those times I
would be willing to bet and I think you
probably could with me that your
fingernails the process in your body
that makes your fingernails grow pauses
stops because you're prioritizing other
things it's do I need to run from this
wolf or is is this the ideal time to be
sending whatever the [__] cells are
that you send to your fingernails to
make your fingernails grow whatever does
that make sense to you
yeah well then actually there's a lot of
like more reasoning in that like you
really hit the nail on the head when it
comes to being like in a fight-or-flight
stay because you stop digesting okay
that's why I think people have other
digestive issues because they're always
stressed was put you in a fighter flight
and you also the prefrontal cortex your
brain the big half in the front just
shuts off and you just use your lower
portion of the brain so you actually
don't that's why standardized testing is
really bad because it puts kids in a
stressful state in the part of their
brain that thinks well turns off because
they're stressed dude it's this it seems
so simple to me okay so so same thing so
there's this warfare your heart rates
elevated your fingernails are not
growing gear you're not your poop
situation isn't happening
your stomach's in pain because you're
you're not digesting you're not doing
these like slow calm things that your
body's always doing you notice how when
you get a cut on your finger and a
couple days it heals this is your body's
always okay I need to do this prioritize
this oh it seems to be that there's a
cut here the pain indicates that your
body without you thinking about you have
listener do you remember sitting
crisscross applesauce last time you got
a cut and saying mmm please you know my
finger no you don't have to your body
just does it when you're in the right
state so so backing up this Wolf's
situation you're in your backyard
this wolf happening let's back up a step
farther this wolf is not here so you're
back to where you're in your backyard
and you're calm the wolf thing
hasn't happened yet you just backed up a
few well instead of the wolf coming
someone text you on your phone in that
text says I hate what you represent what
whoever you think you are
they're coming for it and they're like
you're an idiot DJ's are total [__]
there they spit in the face of musicians
Jake
I hate DJ's their crap here's why I just
get a text out of nowhere it just says
that my heart rate whoo it's kind of
picking up like what do you mean I am a
DJ in you're insulting DJ's which means
that you are insulting me again the
situation there's no wolf still there's
no wolf at all your heart rates picking
up and picking up and then I'm Twitter
fingers back to him I'm still my back
here are my heart it's picking up let's
say I have 15 minutes of like responding
even if I'm not like mad I'm not like
[__] you bro I'm literally just
defending myself and I'm kind of just
I'm like look man I'm glad I got that
out you know that kind of intense that
uh look you gotta you got to get this
out like they don't know about me so I
have to tell them about me do you think
that that is anywhere near at all the
feeling that we're getting people who
take 15 minutes to be aggressive do you
think that's anywhere comparable to this
wolf approaching you the feeling that we
get the that let's say just just from
our body's perspective of like turning
fight-or-flight on oh it's the same
thing your body doesn't know any
difference right at all to me this is a
profound thing do I think a lot of
listeners do I think that a lot of
people do not realize that just even
responding to text reading shitty things
on Facebook seeing that this person just
died 24-hour news all these things they
literally keep you locked into this
fight or flight situation there's no
wolf following you at all times because
of the [__] that you think you need to
fight and the question is are you gonna
feed it though you're gonna feed the
wolf so like you can look at all these
things and you really just choose to get
upset about it like that guy text you
hey man DJ suck do you care about that
the dude you know really care about well
[__] that guy this opinion doesn't
matter like you can't let opinions of
people that you don't care about affect
you at all
so having more fortitude and allowing
what affects human doesn't is definitely
a piece of this but also just not even
looking at it helps as well like I would
say 80 to 85% of social media is
probably negative I mean even if they're
memes like there's not a lot of positive
memes like jokes are pretty derogatory
inherently which is funny I love jokes
they're great but of memes to memes are
awesome you can't live your whole
existence just being a meme can't be a
meme or you know well you can't be me
more but it's probably good money design
where I guess but the the body doesn't
know the difference between you getting
in an argument and having a like a
stress dump or you are about to be eaten
it's the same exact response can we talk
about the long-term effects that like it
just in your opinion like take a look at
like like let's say we have two people
this just the most simple experiment
ever this person is in a Firefly it
responds because they get notifications
every 15 minutes and it's enough for
them to respond or they watch the news
or something corner of their eye every
15 to 20 minutes it keeps them in so
person on the Left blue person is their
fight flight because they're getting a
lot of notifications person on the right
red person over the course of 15 years
they both grow up one person gets
notifications and has Facebook one
person doesn't their health over the
course of 15 years of let's say in this
analogy so every waking hour their
fight-or-flight is turned on they're
connected to social media because they
have notifications from their phone and
they're fairly popular in this situation
okay 15 years so stress management has
been my utmost important thing in
training people and helping people so
this is gonna be I'm glad you asked so
let's in this hypothetical situation
let's say that this person on social
media this is an Asif stressor because
I'm assuming that some people it's not
so I'm just gonna act like that's not a
thing for this so what happens when you
get stressed your body's not in a state
of healing so sympathetic nervous system
flight action you have the pit of
adrenaline your body's ignoring
functions like digestion and eeling and
recovering so you're inherently gonna
have more gut issues I think that's a
big part of it when your cortisol is
high you have a higher insulin Center
insulin insensitivity so your cells
reject like your muscle cells and your
liver cells reject insulin which carries
nutrients to places and then they just
get backlog and they will put on body
fat so this person is going to hold more
body fat be less healthy their
respiration rate and so the rate that
they're breathing is gonna be faster
than others which is going to cause like
knots and a lot of tension in their
upper chest and upper back I read a
study that our respiration rates have
increased in the last 300 years by like
double because people are more stressed
so people are breathing twice as much
that's huge I mean that's that's a huge
thing I think so much which is super
indicative of really poor breathing
habits which can cause a lot of knots in
your upper back and in your mid-back
I've actually seen people when they do a
lot of breath work and learn how to
breathe correctly the diaphragm they
stop having knots like all the regions
in their back they always get and all
this neck pain just kind of goes away
and that posture gets better the this
person is going to be more than likely
more rational because they're always
living in this state of being hyper
aroused which doesn't allow for a lot of
like inductive and deductive reasoning
because the firm part of their brain
that does reasoning just isn't really
ever on because they're always in
fight-or-flight mode is this the same
part of your brain that when you drink
too much alcohol turns off you know I
don't know I think it is or is it the
hippocampus it it it turns your
hippocampus off because that's what
records memory but it also increases
your emotional output which I don't know
what side of the brain that is but
that's what I'll call does to you it's
weird if you just see I see a little
connection and the way that let's see
what else
sleeps so cortisol is a master stress
hormone and a little bit good you need
it to wake up it helps mobilize fatty
acids so you do need it but having it
always around is really detrimental
excuse me because it's really gonna
affect your sleep because you need to
get into a parasympathetic stay to sleep
sleep seems to be like the it's
something for me that I always I knew it
was like I do to sleep it in this is
always repeated a lot of podcast - it's
like sleep is like yeah I know but like
you always kind of seemed like sleep is
something that I'm gonna work on later
in my life you know sleep is the master
key to life because in order to actually
fight cortisol and are really hyper
because we don't live the world now is
not how our bodies are designed to
navigate there's too many things it's
too hyper stress you have too much stuff
to do so you already are at a higher
propensity for having really high stress
levels and sleep is the best way to
mitigate these things sadly it's really
hard to sleep in you're stressed because
you haven't got a lot of cortisol and
it's an arousing chemical so how do we
combat this meditation breathwork eating
quality meals so here's a fun fact when
people get really stressed out they tend
to binge on carbohydrates like oh let's
go eat ice cream so carbohydrates are a
way for your body to naturally deal with
or counterbalance cortisol so that's why
I'm not super into no carb and I also
think you should eat some carbs before
bed because it will help you sleep this
is what I mean when I say your
intelligence will turn against you I say
that phrase often like your body's
trying to help you out he's trying to
get it for you you know like oh I know
that this substance is in Karp's so I'm
gonna eat carbs but it's like but we
find the justification of why do I want
carbs it's because of this actually this
is what I like this is my interests or
whatever it is just this quirky meme I
mean ice cream I'm sad team Nutella yeah
but it's not good to just binge on food
because you're stressed though you got a
look at why you're stressed in the first
place like this is just a product of
this you need to figure out why this is
happening and maybe change or even if
it's something you can't control
find a way to mitigate this because the
quickest way you're gonna die is to be
really stressed out you get Alzheimer's
from not sleeping high cortisol which is
essentially plaque builds up in your
brain and then it stops functioning
really well which
sleep actually flushes a lot of that out
and the problem is when you're really
stressed out you can't sleep so I would
go on a limb and say stress is the
number one killer because it increases
heart rate lack of sleep you don't eat
as well you don't eat as much so so a
lot of times I get hung up when I'm like
what I'm doing like a little bit of
individual or work with people a huge
thing that's that doesn't seem to click
and it didn't click a lot for me is a
lot of people dude yeah I know this I'm
stressed and I can't sleep like me I'd
be like yeah dude of course I can't
sleep because I have nightmares and I
don't want to sleep and I feel shitty
waking up and blah blah I have all these
things of like I didn't realize it but I
was in the victim I was like it's like
these things are happening to me and I
think I can do nothing about them and
you would say I would say phrases like I
got tried whatever I've tried whatever
but it's like then now that I actually
have spent so much time really trying
the breath work not just using it for
when I am anxious but like doing it
every morning for a month or doing and
every morning for four this week or
doing breath work right before bed or
doing yoga and stretches for five
minutes before bed like do it like doing
these things and making sure you really
do them for a long stint of time you
realize that if you're lucky enough to
form the habit you know you can you
realize that okay I am actually sleeping
better oh and you have these little
tools to actually navigate so I think
that a lot of people do they don't
realize it but they get stuck in the
victim part of I do feel these things
yeah it must be easy for you to say
dummy because I would love to just sleep
a good night yeah that'd just be nice if
it was as easy as that yeah bro I tried
that a lot of people will tell me how I
tried that and realistically it's like
give me the honest truth have you tried
it more than once or twice because I
think that people really need to to not
be so instant about like you can't take
a pill and just not be stressed in your
whole world is perfect you get a
wonderful night's sleep you know maybe
you can but what's the long-term effects
of that I think we need to look at our
healing and like how do I make my sleep
not better this week as I'm 27
some 28 whatever we need to look at how
do i overall improve my health like how
do i change the way that i long term do
things how do i make it to where i
do breath work for the rest of my life
and get good sleep these things I and I
think that it's important I think that
it's not staying stuck in that I've I
can't do it I I know these things and I
would love for that man
but I'm where I'm at I think just
knowing that you can change and knowing
that step by step these things there is
ways you said some to me I thought was
really funny it's very short quippy
that's a nice excuse bro I just thought
that was so funny cuz I came for what I
was gonna do but you're like hey man you
should do this no my god man I don't
know if I had time you're like it's cool
excuse my dam you're right I think about
that all the time now III couldn't say
that to everybody
you're a very recieving friend like we
have this like we know each other's
[__] and we know that the real you
and I Spencer like we know that we want
the best for each other we're know like
would want to be these but these big
versions of ourselves not the lower
conscious like just eating [__]
ruffles all day you know so like when
I'm able to say nice excuse bro you were
able to say damn it you're right thanks
like immediately you're like it caught
you and I'm sure wherever you were at
your shoulders probably lowered and
you're like uh-huh son of a [__] I
thought it was funny but it was it was
very valid and I think I mean the
problem is oh yeah I try to sleep good
well yeah everyone tries to sleep good I
mean you can't just decide oh I'm gonna
go to bed one hour earlier and that's
gonna solve the problem like sleep is a
very highly complicated thing and
there's a lot of [__] in your life
that's making it not function very well
and you should probably start weeding
things out and the phone is a [__] for
sleep because the blue light from it
keeps you up so blue light exposure it
comes from the Sun usually and we didn't
have artificial light when we were
evolving so when you your eyes see blue
light they're like okay the sun's out so
we're awake surviving it emits that so
people I could sit on social media for
like an hour and a half before they go
to bed or just like sit and do nothing
and look at their phone before they
sleep like screen time is not inherently
very good I found myself multiple times
where you're just dreading waking up the
next day so you just will sit for a
couple hours and look at your phone to
prolong the the time travel that is
sleep to tomorrow because you don't want
to do it and just
sighing it's like man tomorrow's gonna
happen as probably go to bed that was
hopeful turning a half of all the lights
off in your house throughout two to
three hours where you go to bed really
helpful for seven eight breath tempo
right before bed so four seconds in hold
for seven out for eight should help you
sleep a lot mm-hmm
no caffeine past noon or at least eight
hours before you go to bed this is
something I always take a pin in because
there was another thing that I was I
wasn't honest with myself about is the
caffeine thing I was like no I need
caffeine because I work at this and I'm
a DJ and I stay up these hours and I
don't need sleeping blah blah I don't
have three monsters a day and I'm like
oh I need this because then I'm gonna
get headaches and then I need this
pre-workout or I can't work out all
these excuses but it's good enough oh
dude caffeine there is a weight like it
like I went from that to to for a while
which is zero caffeine like I and I
didn't die my head didn't explode I felt
uncomfortable for a few days and I had a
headache but I just I just itched read
through it so yeah when I was really
depressed and anxious under caffeine for
five months and nothing changed like my
life it actually I had more steady
energy but the reason that I like
caffeine is I just like the I just like
the stimulant feeling it's not that I
need to be awake I just like to be extra
awake so and then I will find myself at
like 7:00 I'm like damn I would love an
energy drink because it would feel great
but I'm trying to sleep tonight so
caffeine's got a half-life of six hours
so that means at hour six half of it's
still in your system and that compounds
so if you drink 300 milligrams at 12 at
6 W hundred and fifty at 12 there be 75
but if you drink multiple doses of
caffeine so if you drink 312 and 304
like you now just have there's a like a
lot of it floating around in your system
and it binds to a receptor the adenosine
receptor in your brain which blocks
another thing I think it's it's not gaba
but it's it's a molecule that it goes to
the same thing that tells you to go to
bed and that's why it keeps you awake so
it just actually blocks your ability to
sleep fuelie so okay so think about okay
fight with me on this say that you were
talking to me I'm arguing I'm a caffeine
guy and this is something I would also
say even farther is I'm a kind of guy
monsters don't affect me I could have
one on my bedside I can lean over take a
drink and go back to bed
no big deal what would you have to say
about that well just because you are
sleeping doesn't mean it's good sleep at
all I mean yeah it's just not good
necessarily and so after about two weeks
the caffeine high you'll stop having it
but the awakeness of it like that
binding to that receptor of that
molecule is always the same amount of
potency so caffeine will always make you
the same amount of awake it just won't
make you the same amount of stimulated
that's why it just always kind of works
and so even if you're having it to not
have a headache
yeah and if you're if you're really
tolerant to it it's still having that
effect on you whether you like it or not
and just not all sleep is good sleep
either
you like this I think sleep and the
morning should be the most ritualized
part of your life I'm with you on that
elaborate more on that what do you mean
like sleep sleep in the morning how are
they correlated well the morning is just
a good preparation for the day and it
gets you in a good mindset and not
looking at social media is a big part of
that instead what I do like brush my
teeth because the movement helps me wake
up drink a glass of water with some salt
in it getting in the shower bathe take a
cold shower for two minutes and then do
breath work because those two things
they stimulate adrenaline and
norepinephrine Act that's the same thing
they wake you up without caffeine so I
don't actually need to drink caffeine in
the morning because of it get out
meditate Journal and then I eat what's
your what's your mental what are you
what's your thought structure like when
you're in the shower so so for me a huge
thing is I'm always like it doesn't
matter if I'm in a whiny mood if doesn't
matter if I'm sick when I turn turn the
nozzle to cold this is my affirmations
of like Jake you're a good man you're a
strong man you can do this who are you
like the it's my like Tony Robbins
two-minute moment for five minute moment
you know cuz I do I am I do my regular
shower and then have my two to five
minutes afterwards just as well what are
what is your mind like during this
because it neva tably what you want to
do was a record it's cool and you want
to clench up and you want to take that
big but what you
you know you want to be telling your
mind like don't don't take that big big
breath just remain calm keep your
shoulders relaxed you want to be telling
yourself good thoughts - what do you say
Spencer well first off this is cold and
suck it up buttercup it's just like how
you know you got a lift some days you
don't want to know so I can man suck it
up [__] that's what you do mm-hmm
come on Lady yeah you uh you flipped
that to cold and I'll just try to focus
on the actual sensation of it on my skin
rather than I'm cold and that helps a
lot the sensation instead of instead of
feeling like this is cold I know what
cold is saying like what is the feeling
of cold right yeah it's like let's just
like meditating it's so cold that you
can't even think about anything else so
instead of feeling like oh I'm freezing
I want to get out I just like try to
only focus on my actual bodily
experience and not put any mental effort
into it and just be stimulated by it I
actually really enjoy taking cold
showers the pipes have been getting cold
is winter and it's been a little rough
but I do it ever seen their scene yeah
it's funny it's something that I have
probably been doing for a year and a
half I mean at least a year now and it
is it's something that it doesn't even
it just it's a subconscious thing I just
turned the water to call it at the end
of my shower like it like there is a
couple times where sometimes I'll get
out of the shower if I'm like not at my
home or I'll like take a hotel shower or
something and I'll get out in I wouldn't
have it's almost like my body's like
what are you doing you didn't do the
cold thing because I'll forget and I'll
honestly get back in and do it cold
really quick before drying off if I had
forgotten because it's it's an enjoyable
thing so listener if it seems kind of
crazy and you're like why would I want
to be uncomfortable I'm doing a cold
shower what's the benefit of that in the
morning there's plenty of benefits you
can research those for days and days but
to advocates here Spencer and I it does
get better and it becomes something that
you enjoy and I think that making sure
you insert either a present moment like
just feel the water on your skin
concentrate on your breath perhaps or
even like I do sometimes you know be
that Tony Robbins be that cheerleader
like be like come on man you're a beast
what are you gonna do today
all right cool we're gonna tackle it
we're gonna kick ass we're gonna smell
super good because we're just a shower
doing it whatever you got to do just
like hi Pierre
that beer Heitmann every morning you
know and and see how think about how
your day is going to be how you're gonna
approach your problems with that mindset
versus arguing about someone who is the
opposite side of the political spectrum
than you know for 35 minutes during your
morning cup of coffee on Facebook just
wondering how your day is gonna be
different
maybe a little I would assume maybe a
little and then the night time that's
just that this is your time to wind down
I had a client it's just a business
owner one of the most high high stress
people I've ever met in my whole life
and and you just got a you got a line
down like you can't just go home like
this and go to bed like if you just will
take the time it's like 30 minutes and
just relax set the phone down just
breathe for a while like drink some
water enjoy yourself just enjoy doing
nothing maybe reflect a little you're
gonna sleep a lot better yeah I mean it
kind of like we talked about in b-pack
says the same thing like just going on a
walk is sometimes you know like
sometimes what's more important then I
need to get depend right the [__] now is
instead of getting 30 minutes of laying
in bed on your phone trying to get tired
because you need to get to bed right now
what if you took 30 minutes of not going
to bed but just winding down and maybe
slowly doing the dishes or slowly taking
a short walk in your own home by
yourself or journaling or something
finding some way to wine down Spencer
what are some other ways that you find
to wind down um I never get really wound
up so I have the gift I think everybody
would say that though no I really have
not that wound up though like I could
sleep it basically any moment I were a
watch the tracks on my sleep and an
average sleep latency so how long it
takes you have a bed is like 20 minutes
mine's like 1 to 2 like it's like I
could just lay down and go to bed
whenever I want it's never been a
problem but after wearing this I
realized my sleep quality's not super
great mm-hmm well ok not even that high
qualities go but I just won't sleep long
enough I'm sleeping less time than I
think because I was calculating time in
bed as time sleeping and haven't spent
about an hour in the
running just laying around and I would
spend about just like 30 minutes like
laying around like looking at my phone
or whatever so I was actually getting
like 1 to 2 hours less sleep than I
thought I think that another thing
adding adding your phone to just your
brains view of your bedroom um I don't
really [__] with my phone in the bedroom
anymore it's not a strict I'm not insane
about it I just not like the phone is
never in the bedroom but I pretty much
just used that room to sleep and so I
what in my reasoning for that is is you
know the thing that I tell myself I
might do it if you're in this room
you're sleeping like if you ain't making
the bed or you're not just like saying
good morning to Shaylee whatever it is
you're sleeping like it's sanctuary yeah
and I think that you know I i I'm
granted that like I'm you know my home
here is big enough to where I have about
plenty of other places to do things but
even if you just have a one-bedroom
apartment a studio whatever it is maybe
just make it to where like you make your
bed in the morning and just make a rule
for yourself like I don't touch my phone
in the bed unless I'm double checking my
alarms and then I'm putting it away or
whatever but don't sit on your bed and
text don't but like maybe find a chair
that if you want to be in your room and
text or be on your phone or whatever
just try to like do little things like
it's kind of you know being nice to your
brain and trying to maybe even like work
on that placebo try it out just be like
when I'm in my room
I don't touch my phone in my bed they do
not combine it's just a rule that I have
you just don't make a habit of it I mean
real life is just dictated by habits in
general if you make a habit to not do
that you won't I'm gonna go on some
woowoo stuff that I just can't
empirically prove at all but I'm pretty
sure this affects you Wi-Fi signals are
radio waves and your brain works on
frequencies and I don't think it's
probably that helpful to have them on
when you're sleeping so unplug your
router also your phone lets off EMF
frequencies which can really affect just
your natural circadian rhythm and your
output I've done I've seen other people
do this this is just like a little gem
experiment you have your phone flat on
your skin and from what I've noticed
I can prove any of this is that I have
less work output and b-pack said the
same thing that's actually why I tried
this like he can and he can have he has
worse
if his phone's touching his skin so if
you're gonna have in your bedroom at
least put on airplane mode mm-hmm
when maybe that's something that we can
all perform you know like just sit like
you know you don't have to just believe
it just because we're just some dudes
talking about it try it out maybe try a
little areas if you're like we're like
whatever other people's version of
working out while touching their phone
like try to try to have an intuitive
10-minute conversation with your phone
just in your hand not looking at it just
hanging by your right side versus your
phone not touching you at all do
sometimes I notice even just the
distraction of it must be our
subconscious like oh I know my phones
over here sometimes when I meditate in
the morning I have to chuck my phone all
the way across the room even if I'm
using an app or something because I
don't want if I do any sort of open eye
meditation I don't want the corner of my
eye to catch my phone and try to be like
yeah why why is a reason why Jake needs
to feel dopamine right now in your brain
will find the reason to grab that phone
so so you were talking about he just has
sitting on his lap so in his pocket
oh oh okay yeah right pocket I just
think that we're well I know that we're
very highly sensitive to a lot of things
that were not aware of because they're
not necessarily tangible and it's
probably kind of just like how people
were born by power plans a lot of them
will get like terrible cancer if you're
like buy a power station like these
things are emitting some form of energy
or frequency and it's probably affecting
you I can't tell you what 100% is but I
would bet my life on it
this is affecting in some way and it
definitely affects sleep for a myriad of
reasons so get an alarm blog yeah I
agree I think that that noticing all
those little things that well I kind of
compared to sent so it's like I can't
see it you know it's another one those
things I can't see Bluetooth signals I
can't see Wi-Fi but it's floating around
and it doesn't directly affect me like
blah blah blah but think about if you
didn't have a nose and people were just
farting all around you you wouldn't know
that you're just breathing there fart
air man think about that beer you're
just like if you if right now I just
[__] my pants on this podcast I just
poop and you're listening or you're
listening your nose is listening if you
didn't have a nose you wouldn't be
to smell it and there's some like toxic
gases that are sent list and that's
definitely there you don't know it don't
they put I don't think put they make the
smell of something natural gas natural
gas I smelled like eggs yeah they could
make it smell like strawberries a
pleasant really unpleasant so you go
away and don't die I feel like you we
you know what is it what sense do to us
we do get offended a sense like when
something smells bad you're not like
what is that smell you always want to
blame it on someone you notice that you
like who's cooking that [__] or like Oh
Longview or oh the mills or Oh like it
yeah every time you smell something that
you don't like you want to blame someone
right away you notice that so horrible
you can display quell dissent just
change and this scent is not
particularly like the scent that it was
before I have a very sensible factory
system and sentence really put me off so
living here is kind of hard I'm huge on
I'm huge on sense too I feel like I I'm
just very sensitive to sense mm-hmm
probably just sleep better I know it's
not that easy but third of your life and
it's the most important recovery time so
that's a couple good tips on unsleeping
better I think adding blackout curtains
like - JD's room is a cave of darkness
it should be they black out curtains
whoo I think they're like $10 at one - I
mean I think people should prioritize
their sleep more just like whatever you
can do to whatever sleep you are getting
how about that just make it the best it
can't be you know where they wear
whatever clothes you need to be that to
be the comfiest put your phone in a
different place lock out the curtains
spend $10 on a fan that has just a
little bit of background noise or when
you're making cuts to your life because
you don't have enough time to do all
your stuff
don't cut sleep people like to do that
people like they've got okay so if they
have a schedule and it's got room for
two blocks
and it's got like work play and sleep
for three blocks yeah well maybe go to
bed and it's gonna be way more
beneficial for you like stop like
cutting sleep time to do other
superfluous things that are deaf
not as important yeah sometimes I do I
have this I'm like I'm an artist I don't
want to lose this thought like I'll be
like working on some super shitty beat
or something late and I'm convinced that
it's super good and I'm like I can't go
to bed blah blah blah but it's
realistically like if I reuse revisit it
in the morning would have be way more
more slept and more rounded about about
the subject whatever it is that you're
working on in the morning after you have
some sleep you're gonna handle it better
you're gonna handle the thirty minutes
of being super tired kind of shitty but
you're gonna handle thirty minutes of
being well-rested and feeling awake and
fruitful you're kind of getting more
done in that thirty minutes
sleep is important Spencer just breathe
just breathe breathe from your belly and
I think breathing we were talking about
are we getting up here on time I believe
so yeah yeah like ten fifteen so let's
end it with this we're talking about
something that Shelley was telling me
she had she had essentially a patient
while back ago that was had been in the
military and they were able to slow
their heart rate very quickly and they
were able to like as she was taking
their heart rate just slow it down slow
their breathing way down and she was
talking about this and I I'm able to do
that too now it's something that I
wasn't able to do before I even though
I've been sitting this person for a long
time many years it's something that I I
don't think that I had the ability to do
I had terrible anxiety all these things
and now I can put my hand on my heart my
heart's being super super fast and I
could see like an eight to ten second
breath out and I could slow my heart
rate very quickly this is something
we're talking about this is a super good
thing like there's something that like
was a casual conversation between Shane
and I but I'm like oh this can be taught
I used to not do this and within the
last year I've learned how to do it so
can you expand on this like how good
this is like not even just for anxiety
attacks but just having this ability to
like slow our heart rates yeah it's
awesome to do that because you're now
less stressed
how many deep breaths put you in a pair
of sympathy no state which is healing
feeding feeling it's nice and well it's
just regenerative and it's now
or people usually are because they're
stressed out so like snipers will reduce
our heart rate or like ninjas would
reduce their heart rate and to almost
like nothing to appear dead
yes it's very cool so short you can also
do it both ways to like you gonna get
real excited for like a sporting event
or like a lift like quick and quick out
quick and cool you want nice slow
pulling inhale and then an even slower
excel even hold it for a couple seconds
at the top for really going to bed for
in 7 hold 8 out it's really gonna drive
you to sleep I really like that one
there's a TED talk actually on this I
don't remember it's something about
search TED talks and breath dude the
breath is the Forgotten art so anti chi
chi is breath it's breath energy like
people like to think it's like this
metaphysical like magic it's just the
utilization of breath to output more
force because they know if they could
lock down on their diaphragm and control
this breath they could output more force
so right the ability to control the
breath I mean it's something you do a
lot you breathe a lot and it's just we
it's an autonomic thing so we don't put
a lot of stock into it it's kind of the
first thing you ever did if you think
about it when you got out the the veg
canal you just took a big old breath air
I just think if you're trying to solve
problems just keep following it back
what's the problem what's the problem we
need to start winning to start I mean go
all the way back first thing we did was
breath I'm making connections that don't
really exist but nobody taught us how to
breathe or focus yeah you just did it
yeah but we live in such a complicated
time that now we're actually having to
be like oh we moved so quickly that we
have to like oh what did we use to do to
make sure we're balancing these things
it's something that we didn't realize
we'd never have to do probably as a
species but these are things that we
need to connect with our more primitive
things and learn about them so breath
work is something that it is something
that you need to be patient with it does
have instant effects like you can do it
your first time and have like wow I feel
calm but I'm doing I'm building you kind
of changed the way you breathe I breathe
more for my belly rather than my chest
now and I'm also through like singing
stuff my the muscles around breathing
and your throat and they change there's
all these little micro muscle
however that works are changing and
strengthening in different ways I think
just continually doing things like I
can't imagine the long-term effects of
of continuing all this breadth work I
think it's just gonna be great for
inflammation for all these things them I
did wim HOF breathing method before I
ran like three miles the other day and
it was I was I was pretty far into it
before I started feeling as if I needed
to take deeper breaths like I was able
to I did win my breathing and pretty
much like stood up and got my like
obviously mental clarity and made sure I
was gonna like faint or anything and you
started running and I was able to run
for quite a while in like just a normal
just in and out on an even in and out
breath until I had to start like okay
I'm getting more tired need to extend my
breath or change it up well so if you
want to calm down wim HOF breathing is
not the go-to oh yeah actually yeah yeah
that's a very excited Toria breath work
or like fire like fire breathing is or
like dragon's breath is another
technique excitatory yes like you make a
wake up you don't use that to go down
yeah in first-timers who haven't done
any breath work don't go don't do wim
hof breathing and then go for a run
that's done just well you might pass out
and so just likes it yeah but but it is
a cool thing I'm actually like I said
I've been doing it for a while and it's
things that I've like looked into it's
it's cool it's fun it's enjoyable you
see this is a good example though
because you can do this get really
excited to perform really well but you
can also use breath to go to sleep like
this is just being able this is the
ultimate tool in the toolbox that's free
and it's not that hard you just must and
also people breathe poorly and they use
their upper trap and neck muscles to
pull their ribs up out of the way their
lungs and it causes neck tension so most
people's knots are from breathing poorly
and if they would start to breathe
better their posture and pain would go
away right okay and then do one thing I
do want to end on because I did I tell
you that I did the deprivation tank at
Exedy I think oh you did not tell me
that I did I did the sensory deprivation
tank will end here because we got to get
going here but when it comes to neck I
actually had it my first time there's a
place called forever float in Longview
and I heard about it yeah the gentleman
I think his name is Dave I'll have to
recall that correctly
but he was very nice he was very he told
us all about it it was a very
comfortable and clean place essentially
you lay in a tank of water that
the salt makes Italy water and you
equally buoyant that didn't make sense
you're floating in the water because the
salt water and it equals out with your
body it's the same temperature as your
body so in its dark and essentially
you're floating there and you're able to
relax and obviously I was like focusing
on my breath and trying to to meditate
and after a bit I started noticing pops
in the back of my neck I was actually
releasing tension of my neck that I
didn't know I was holding so over time
like you're in here for an hour and I
would feel more and more and I'm like oh
my gosh I'm like these are things that I
didn't you can't release when your heads
against a pillow because you don't
realize you're holding these little
micro muscles and so I think that anyway
I just wanted to mention the sensory
deprivation think we can go more in
depth on it later on in life but it's
definitely a good thing for for neck
pain and wrath work it's definitely a
good thing for I don't know everything
yes be kind to yourself the kind
yourself take care of yourself I hope
you guys benefit from the advice that
Spencer and I give if you have any
questions I'm just gonna suggest that if
you go over to YouTube and comment that
we will try to respond or try to have
our next conversation around about them
because we just we just want to have
these conversations to really expand on
the little details that can help people
and in fine areas that we have had
success in and relay them and explain
them to people and - so not everybody
has to make the same mistakes that we
make so take care of yourself listener
my
you